<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Beautiful News</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com</link>
	<description>The magazine of tasteful living</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Nov 2021 17:23:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/apple-icon-180x180-150x150.png</url>
	<title>Beautiful News</title>
	<link>https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>L'accès de ce serveur est uniquement pour les cheeseconnaiseur</title>
		<link>https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/mary-quicke-guest-columnist-cheese-connoisseur/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mary Quicke]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Oct 2021 20:13:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Guest Columnist]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mary Quicke]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/?p=6247</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>COVID has been a brutal experience for all of us. Given this impact on human life, talking about the damage to livelihoods could be perceived as insignificant or missing the point. And our livelihood is specialty cheese, and our customers and businesses have been ravaged. I have missed the joy of closeness with my cheese [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/mary-quicke-guest-columnist-cheese-connoisseur/">Every Cloud Has a Silver Lining</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com">Cheese Connoisseur</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>COVID has been a brutal experience for all of us. Given this impact on human life, talking about the damage to livelihoods could be perceived as insignificant or missing the point. And our livelihood is specialty cheese, and our customers and businesses have been ravaged.</p>



<p>I have missed the joy of closeness with my cheese family: farmers, cheesemakers, vendors, people who love cheese. And yet, we’ve all been in this together. There is something about a shared experience, even in the darkest of times, that brings us together. We know we will all measure time by “That was before COVID… that was after COVID”, and we’ll all have the same clock.&nbsp;</p>



<p>There we were, stores full of cheese, our lovely cross-bred cows just coming into the spring flush of lush grass in our rich Devon valley, producing beautiful milk. Suddenly, so many of the ways cheese lovers get our cheese had disappeared. We were suddenly on our own, our sales not there. What were we to do with our cows, our milk, our people, a year’s worth and more of our lovely clothbound cheddar in store? And what was going to happen to all of those great colleagues in the chain whose livelihoods depended on great cheese, those we depended on to tell our story and sell our cheese, including the chefs, cheese sommeliers and the cheesemongers?</p>



<p>One of the most extraordinary and moving things about the crisis was the way our customers reached out to us:</p>



<p>“We love your cheese, but we are locked down, how can we get our hit of Quicke’s?”</p>



<p>&nbsp;“It’s my sister’s birthday, we always celebrate with a platter of your cheese, but the deli counter it was on has closed. Can you help us?”</p>



<p>“My son is self-isolating away at college, and he can’t come home. I know your cheese will cheer him up.”</p>



<p>It was miraculous to hear over and over that people love great cheese, they love our cheese, they wanted it for the precious family moments of life. I know people eat our cheese for that marketing category ‘occasions’. We heard and felt and were summoned by what that means in the warp and weft of peoples’ lives. They reached out and told us, and we were touched and pulled into action:&nbsp; get boxes, curate a cheeseboard of our cheese, cut cheese into home-sized pieces.</p>



<p>People called for them from all over the country, and we pulled people in to help with this who otherwise wouldn’t be working.</p>



<p>Get our website working so it’s easy to buy from. Work out how best to send it off though a courier to keep it in great shape.</p>



<p>And we could respond to all those people who reached out to us, and tell the story of our cheese, that our colleagues in cheese once told in restaurants, on menus and in delis. Cheese lovers let us into their homes and their hearts.&nbsp;</p>



<p>We also found that other cheesemakers, our deli and restaurant cousins in cheese family were also delivering cheese. We collaborate and make more interesting boxes. We connected in a way we hadn’t before. We play with flavors, recommend pairings and deliver those for people to enjoy together.</p>



<p>We have conversations, listen and talk, know how we connect across the world, for the love of cheese. That’s the opportunity for all of us making artisan cheese: we all have a great story to tell, and it’s so rewarding to be able to tell the story and hear from cheese lovers.</p>



<p>Cheese also became national, as cheese connoisseurs leapt to support their own struggling cheesemakers, cheesemongers and cheese sommeliers. The U.S. had ‘Victory Cheese’. The UK had ‘British Cheese Weekender’, an online cheese festival celebrating all things cheesey. That is how it should be. In a time of crisis, look to your own.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Now we are all looking to a time beyond the crisis and the sorrow and the emergency. We know more strongly than ever the power and strength of cheese family. I don’t want to lose the amazing connection we now feel.</p>



<p><em>Mary Quicke is the 14th generation of the Quicke family on Home Farm in the UK and has been running the cheese business since 1987.</em></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/mary-quicke-guest-columnist-cheese-connoisseur/">Every Cloud Has a Silver Lining</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com">Cheese Connoisseur</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Le fromage de votre vie</title>
		<link>https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/ken-whitacre-editorial-cheese-connoisseur/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ken Whitacre]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Oct 2021 20:04:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[editorial]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/?p=6244</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Having been raised in a lower economic region in the state of Kentucky, I count myself truly blessed that I have been able to rise up and travel to many countries and see other cultures from around the world. In fact, my first taste of cheese was most likely that of “government cheese” issued to [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/ken-whitacre-editorial-cheese-connoisseur/">The Cheeses of Our Lives</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com">Cheese Connoisseur</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Having been raised in a lower economic region in the state of Kentucky, I count myself truly blessed that I have been able to rise up and travel to many countries and see other cultures from around the world. In fact, my first taste of cheese was most likely that of “government cheese” issued to families below the poverty line and, according to <em>CheeseWiki.com</em>, “consists of a variety of cheese types and other ingredients such as emulsifiers blended together and may be made of any of cheddar, Colby cheese, cheese curd or granular cheese.&#8221;</p>



<p>Even from my humble origins, I always liked cheese and thought it a great luxury to sometimes order slices of American, cheddar or Colby myself from my neighborhood &#8220;mom-and-pop&#8221; grocer, whose entire family lived above their small corner store. But my voyage — in school, work and life — has led me to broaden my horizons. Going from Kentucky to study at a university in upstate New York quickly opened my eyes to the plethora of cheeses imported into the country and produced by artisans all around the U.S. And after college ended, my first trip outside of the country was to England, where I was introduced to the great nuances of Stiltons and the soft cheeses from Bath.</p>



<p>Over the years, through experiences at domestic and international food shows, business travel and holidays, I have had the pleasure of being further introduced to cheeses from all corners of the globe: Manchego cheese from Spain, Gouda on the banks of Amsterdam, Époisses on the Champs Élysées in Paris, and soft burratas from the south of Italy, just to name a few.</p>



<p>I think of these experiences as I drive back from dropping my eldest child, a daughter, off at college. I remember her as a young girl enjoying grilled cheese sandwiches and macaroni and cheese and, as she grew, her tastes expanded to being a young cheese connoisseur herself, preferring warmed brie with jam and crackers as a snack instead of the junk food many of her friends eat.</p>



<p>As she dives into the college experience, I imagine she will learn so much, not just from classes, but through her dormmates and friends, where they might prepare specialty cheese with just the right crackers and accompaniments during get-togethers. She will travel, too, and maybe find friends from cheese-producing states such as Vermont, Wisconsin, Oregon or California, or even abroad. And she might visit their homes and their cities and, at each place, expand her horizons. The tastes, flavors and smells of the countless specialty cheeses I’ve sampled are now part of my life, all enriching and an important part of me. As my daughter begins her journey, I wish her every success, of course, and I hope she knows that it is okay to sample great cheeses wherever she goes and keep the joys of eating those specialty cheeses with people she cares about as great memories wherever she may be.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/ken-whitacre-editorial-cheese-connoisseur/">The Cheeses of Our Lives</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com">Cheese Connoisseur</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Il faut y gouter !</title>
		<link>https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/jim-prevor-editorial-cheese-connoisseur/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jim Prevor]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Oct 2021 19:59:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[editorial]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/?p=6241</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>One of the beauties of cheese is that it is quite portable and can be eaten at almost any occasion or place and alone as a snack or at night before heading off to bed. Yet, it is also true that specialty cheese is so often the centerpiece of a great party. There are many [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/jim-prevor-editorial-cheese-connoisseur/">Life Must Go On</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com">Cheese Connoisseur</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>One of the beauties of cheese is that it is quite portable and can be eaten at almost any occasion or place and alone as a snack or at night before heading off to bed. Yet, it is also true that specialty cheese is so often the centerpiece of a great party.</p>



<p>There are many reasons for this. First, some cheeses are rich in fats and calories, and one won’t usually eat very much at one time. So, we might not order or serve specialty cheeses at all if we are going to be alone. Second, each cheese has a story… it comes from a certain place, contains special types of milk, say from a cow, goat or sheep and, sometimes, other ingredients are added or accompanied, such as dried fruit. Third, each cheese is served in a certain way, say offered with wine, honey, almonds or prosciutto.</p>



<p>During the depths of the pandemic, some have been able to share extraordinary cheeses with their family, but many, without the conviviality of parties and get-togethers, just haven’t had the occasion to really buy and serve the many specialty cheeses they might have procured and presented back in the pre-COVID days.</p>



<p>For many of us, the availability of vaccines gave a renewed zest to life. We started gatherings with friends and family that we hadn’t had for a year. We got together, shared love and conviviality and the food and drink that are part of human interaction.</p>



<p>Then, as quickly as it came, many of us pulled back from such togetherness. What if some aren’t vaccinated? What if they are, but we experience a break-out incident? How about the risk to children who don’t qualify for vaccines? How can one have much fun if one is worried about things such as this?</p>



<p>Yet, increasingly, the situation reminds us that life must go on. Certainly, there are risks, just as there are risks when one gets in a car, flies in a plane or walks down the street. From a public policy standpoint, there must be, and there are, many efforts to mitigate these risks. Third doses of vaccines have started in Israel and will be standard in America soon. Vaccines for younger children are being submitted for FDA approval. Treatments for people who become infected with COVID are advancing.</p>



<p>The consensus seems to be that, despite the risks, life must go on. Children must go to school, young people must meet and marry, people must build careers. Life, we have learned, requires conviviality, the sharing of joy and celebrations. We need to cheer for births, engagements, weddings and more. This means we need Champagne, wine and other drinks that go with celebrations. And we need to share the sustenance and indulgence of specialty cheese. We learn about the cheese, we learn of memories of cheese well-eaten in days gone by, and we celebrate the opportunity to share great food with people we value and love.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/jim-prevor-editorial-cheese-connoisseur/">Life Must Go On</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com">Cheese Connoisseur</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>FROMAAAGE !</title>
		<link>https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/a-next-generation-cheesemaker-emmi-roths-madeline-kuhn/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lisa White]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Sep 2021 19:21:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cover Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cheesemaker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Emmi Roth]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Madeline Kuhn]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/?p=6158</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Growing up on a small dairy farm in Wisconsin, Madeline Kuhn wasn’t focusing on pursuing a career in dairy or cheese from an early age. It wasn’t until she went off to the University of Wisconsin in Madison that she began zeroing in on a career in food science. “That program has a very strong [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/a-next-generation-cheesemaker-emmi-roths-madeline-kuhn/">A Next Generation Cheesemaker: Emmi Roth&#8217;s Madeline Kuhn</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com">Cheese Connoisseur</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Growing up on a small dairy farm in Wisconsin, Madeline Kuhn wasn’t focusing on pursuing a career in dairy or cheese from an early age. It wasn’t until she went off to the<a href="https://www.wisc.edu"> University of Wisconsin in Madison</a> that she began zeroing in on a career in food science.</p>



<p>“That program has a very strong dairy presence,” she says.</p>



<p>It was right after she graduated college in 2017 that Kuhn accepted a job with Monroe, WI-based <a href="https://www.emmiroth.com">Emmi Roth</a> in the company’s research and development department. It turns out the craft cheesemaker/importer and position were a perfect fit. In a short period of time, she has been instrumental in iconic Emmi Roth product launches.</p>



<p>“I was familiar with their cheese prior to applying there,” she says.</p>



<p><em>Cheese Connoisseur</em> spoke with Kuhn about growing up on a Wisconsin dairy farm and how that propelled her into her current role and successes at Emmi Roth. Those seeking a career in the cheese industry are sure to be inspired by her story.</p>



<p><strong>CC: Talk about your life growing up on a farm.</strong></p>



<p><strong>M.K.:</strong> Our family farm is located in Wisconsin’s Buffalo County in Fountain City. It’s a tiny river town on the Mississippi River with rolling bluffs and an idyllic landscape. This was the setting from my childhood. I have great memories interacting with the natural world around me in fields. I especially felt great joy and pride in working with the animals, especially cows. It was an excellent way to grow up, and I was happy to have that experience. It’s a rare experience for young people now. But it made me very aware of these natural cycles or processes, watching seasons, landscape changes and harvests as well as the births of livestock and wildlife. I watched them grow and develop and become part of our small, family-owned farm. It really instilled that love for the landscape but also agriculture production, which is at the heart of what I do now working in the cheese industry. It also is how I try to approach many things in my life, knowing my place, where things start and having respect for it.</p>



<p>Our farm had a relatively small herd and was solely family run. We milked around 60 Jersey cows, all pasture raised, with rotational grazing. That was how we approached eating and utilizing the change of seasons and bringing the cows nutrition from the land. We didn’t do any row cropping, just hay harvest, but the farm did work with a local dairy coop where the milk was used to produce cheddar.</p>



<p>I worked the farm and was very involved in everyday chores and the upkeep. There were age-appropriate tasks. Being the youngest, I spent a lot of time with the calves, making sure they were socialized and friendly. They had to get used to having people around them, touching them and working with them. I fed them milk. Seeing them head out to pasture was really a special experience. My folks still live on the farm but retired from dairy farming. Although there are no cows, they still enjoy the beautiful setting and remain dedicated to regenerative and responsible land and energy management. This protects the soil, slopes and forests. Dairying can be a tough way of life, and they milked for precisely eight years and four days while raising three children.</p>



<p><strong>CC: How did you end up pursuing a</strong> <strong>food science degree?</strong></p>



<p><strong>M.K.:</strong> At the end of high school is when I decided to pursue a food science degree and career. The University of Wisconsin in Madison has a highly-respected food science department with experts in several food science topics, so it made sense to go to school there. Also, my dad is an alumni of the school, so I was interested in following that same route that he took. And I was thrilled to be accepted there, and go to my dream school. Unlike many freshman, I didn’t flip flop my major. I happened to have a clear sense of what was for me.</p>



<p>When I approached graduation, I felt the same way. I was still very interested and excited about food science. Before I graduated in 2017, I had contact with advisers in the school’s food science department who were interested in preparing students for productive and active careers in the field. I was coming from a small class in high school and a tiny town, so it was important to me to have guidance and people in my corner. That definitely played a big role in my success and time at school. I had advisers and professors who would go above and beyond to give students the kind of support they needed. Because food science was a smaller department at the time, they could do that. Other specialties didn’t have the same ability. I felt supported and encouraged. If you find yourself in that environment, you’re better situated to explore the field and the type of work or projects that speak to you, and I was able to do that. I was fortunate. I also greatly enjoyed and appreciated the actual dairy part of the department. The University of Wisconsin, Madison, has an excellent dairy-focused program and resource facility. They also have a pilot plant on site that runs jointly with the <a href="https://www.cdr.wisc.edu">Department of Dairy Research</a>. Here, they make cheese, bottle milk, make ice cream, etc. It’s not only a place for students to do part time work but also designed for learning and labs and getting experience with the hands on part of dairy and the dairy industry. It’s a great resource to have on site for students. I had my sights on food science and taking that path, but I couldn’t have guessed or imagined I would end up in the dairy or cheese industry.</p>



<p><strong>CC: How did the opportunity at Emmi Roth come about?</strong></p>



<p><strong>M.K.:</strong> I was feeling very lucky to have something lined up after graduation. Like my classmates, I was seeking any and all jobs to apply for. At the time, the job prospect market for those with a food science education background was a bit tight. As new graduates, we were competing with those who had graduate degrees and PhDs. That was always a concern. So amongst my applications was a position at Emmi Roth as a research development technician. It was R&amp;D focused, and I thought that was interesting. Also, it was cheese and dairy with a well-known and highly regarded and awarded company. I was encouraged when I heard back from them, then meeting with my future manager I felt even more like this had some legs. It seemed like a great place to start my career. I was even more excited to be offered the job, which I accepted and became a part of Emmi Roth.</p>



<p><strong>CC: How has your career at Emmi Roth unfolded?</strong></p>



<p><strong>M.K.: </strong>I’ve been working for Emmi Roth for over four years, and a lot has happened in that time. At our creameries in Wisconsin, we focus on creating and innovating products for our Roth brand of cheeses. The business has changed and so has the structure of our department. I’ve had a lot of great experiences. As part of the R&amp;D team, I focus on new product development. I play an active part in the ideations of new items, building the recipe, formula and process to go with products and bringing it to production to present to our customers and consumers. The second half of my responsibilities is continuous improvement, anything and everything involved in helping our award-winning products be the best they can be. This includes solving and addressing any quality or production issues. I’m also a licensed cheesemaker. I achieved this certification in my first year with the company. To do so, I completed work experience and course work, then passed the exam. Wisconsin is the only state that requires a license to make cheese. We have a dedicated team of licensed cheesemakers on staff. The licensing was important for me because I’m developing new products.</p>



<p><strong>CC: Talk about your proudest career accomplishments.</strong></p>



<p><strong>M.K.:</strong> I’ve been involved in several successful new product launches since I’ve been here. Early in my career at Emmi Roth, I inherited a project to bring to market. This was a soft-ripened cheese that later became known as Roth Monroe cheese. It’s a beautiful, smear-ripened, small format cheese. There were some unique considerations to make that product in our current facility due to the size and amount of attention and care it required. It was a unique project to tackle. We went on to produce and sell this cheese for over two years, but it is temporarily not available. That was my first new item success story. I like to go after those unique varieties, and this was a passion project.</p>



<p><strong>CC: What are you working on now?</strong></p>



<p><strong>M.K.:</strong> We’re always working on something. We just had a busy season. Recently, we launched the new Roth Aged Gouda, which was something I worked on for three years. That is one of my favorite cheeses we make, and it’s a recipe of mine. At the same time, we were working on developing some new flavored Goudas to add to our current portfolio. I was involved in a project that was a consumer-driven campaign. Our team did the legwork to develop new Gouda recipes, then rolled it out to our social media fans online and let them vote on their favorite flavor. Then that would be the one we’d make. It was a unique campaign that was crowd sourced; Roth hasn’t done that before, so it was exciting to be a part of it. The result was our Roth Spinach Artichoke Gouda that is currently available online through Amazon Fresh. We went on to keep the momentum from our flavored Gouda campaign to work on new exciting flavors for the Roth line. Now some of these varieties are available, like Hot Honey, Buffalo Ranch and Serrano Cilantro, and we’ll have more coming through the rest of the year. That is an ongoing project, and we’re just getting off the ground on those new items. Flavored cheese gets a lot of people’s attention. We have great flavored cheeses already so it’s natural to keep building on that.</p>



<p><strong>CC: Talk about your involvement in the industry and importance of this.</strong></p>



<p><strong>M.K.:</strong> I attend conferences including <a href="https://www.cheesesociety.org">ACS</a> (American Cheese Society), and we enter in as many contests as much as possible. My involvement in that is to help select cheeses to send to contests. It is less about winning than about the judging process, which we can learn from to better our products. We try to keep our presence in contests as much as we can, while reminding people that winning isn’t everything. Sure, it’s nice to win awards, but we need to use the opportunity and feedback to be better at what we do. The good thing about the cheese industry is there are incredible people involved in contests who really just want to help the producers. They are there to do a service for them, and we should take advantage of that when we can.</p>



<p>Also, I’m a member of the <a href="https://www.wischeesemakersassn.org">Wisconsin Cheesemakers Association</a>, which is active in events, conferences and education. They offer opportunities to network and keep people involved. I try to stay involved with that. It’s important in this industry to use those outlets as much as I can and be a part of that community. The Wisconsin Cheesemakers Association puts an emphasis on that. It caters to and offers outreach and activities for everyone, but especially to young professionals in the cheese and dairy industry. That’s encouraging to me.</p>



<p><strong>CC: What do you like best about the cheese industry?</strong></p>



<p><strong>M.K.:</strong> I couldn’t imagine I would work in the dairy industry growing up, let alone the cheese industry. I’m thankful I had this experience and entry with Emmi Roth. It showed me the level of dedication and passion that is involved in producing cheese in Wisconsin and just how that attention to detail and the use of technology and science was intimately intertwined with the art and craft of producing cheese. That really spoke to me. I always considered myself to be a creative, artistic person with scientific motivation and an understanding of how things work as well as how physical transformations happen. To find an industry that combines those things was huge. Science and art are still my favorite parts of cheese, but I like to go deeper into the cheesemaking principals. Cheese is a historic food that has been produced all over the world for centuries, so the principals of making cheese have not changed a lot. We can use technology and tools to understand the process and principals but the actual process hasn’t changed. There is a lot to learn being in a segment of the industry in R&amp;D to play around and tackle problem solving and dig into challenges. Sometimes cheese can be frustrating but it is very rewarding for me.</p>



<p><strong>CC: What are your career aspirations?</strong></p>



<p><strong>M.K.:</strong> I hope to continue to bring inspired creations to Roth. I see this as a great place to serve our customers with approachable but elevated cheese. That’s important because cheese is an indulgent food but it can still be a bit intimidating. I appreciate Roth is living in the elevated but approachable space, and I like living in that space, too. I look forward to continuing to participate in the future of the industry, in general, as well as offer new products moving forward for a healthy cheese industry. It’s timely and very important for young people in this industry to get involved and participate and continue innovation and sustainability. These are things that will be scrutinized even more in the future. I’m hoping to be a part of that and to show how this very traditional historic industry is changing and the opportunities that come with that.</p>



<p><strong>CC: Talk about the opportunity for diversity in the cheese industry.</strong></p>



<p><strong>M.K.:</strong> I would agree that in Wisconsin especially where we have a registry of licensed cheesemakers and a renowned program that supports master cheesemakers, which is the next level, you can see there is disparity there. Because there are not that many women, there are many opportunities, but I see it out of necessity. After decades of hard work and dedication in the cheese world, we have cheese pros retiring or leaving the cheese industry. In order to preserve the traditions and artistry of cheesemaking and tackle hot topics like continued innovation and sustainability, we need infusion of new energy; that is essential. We need people with diverse life experiences with different trade backgrounds, and those who don’t come from traditional dairy or ag roots like me. There aren’t that many of us, so it’s a huge opportunity to increase diversity in all levels of the industry, not just women but others from different life circumstances. We need as many people as we can. I can’t define what that looks like but I look forward to how they learn and remaster this ancient craft and bring it into a bright future. I also look forward to playing an active part in it. It’s helpful to have people bring in an alternative view. How do we help our career dairy farmers step back and get a better perspective on what we currently have in producing dairy? Where are the opportunities? It’s helpful to step back and bring in different perspectives; at the farm level that is hugely beneficial for even the established folks who’ve had a very rich and rewarding career in the industry. It’s okay to shake it up when we have to. </p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/a-next-generation-cheesemaker-emmi-roths-madeline-kuhn/">A Next Generation Cheesemaker: Emmi Roth&#8217;s Madeline Kuhn</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com">Cheese Connoisseur</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Fromage Grecq</title>
		<link>https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/greek-cheese-cheese-connoisseur/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[R.M. Peluso]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Sep 2021 19:12:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Feature]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Feta]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Greece]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Greek cheeses]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/?p=6190</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Cheeses from Greece have a storiedhistory and widespread appeal. Say “Greek cheese” and most people think feta. But the cheese heritage of Greece is ancient, rich, and far more varied. Greeks had been producing and trading many fresh and aged cheese types well before the 8th Century B.C. We know this because Homer wrote about [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/greek-cheese-cheese-connoisseur/">Greek Cheese:  It&#8217;s Not Just Feta</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com">Cheese Connoisseur</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="has-medium-font-size">Cheeses from Greece have a storied<br>history and widespread appeal.</p>



<p>Say “Greek cheese” and most people think feta. But the cheese heritage of Greece is ancient, rich, and far more varied. Greeks had been producing and trading many fresh and aged cheese types well before the 8th Century B.C. We know this because Homer wrote about it. How much earlier were the Greeks making cheese? Archeology tells us that cheesemaking spread through trade and religion from Sumeria sometime after the 4th Millennium B.C. Cheese served as ritualistic offerings to Mesopotamian deities that would later appear in the Greek pantheon. The god Aristaious, according to legend, taught humans the art of cheesemaking, and the cult of Asklepios performed healing rituals involving milk coagulation, an essential step in making cheese.</p>



<p>With the collapse of the Bronze age Mycenaean civilization, around 1200 B.C., Greece fell into a dark age lasting several centuries. Cheesemaking then spread with the Greek diaspora to Anatolia, Cyprus and other points around the Aegean, Ionian and Mediterranean seas. Greece recovered its former glory and, by Homer’s time, plant (fig) and animal rennet were used to produce fresh cheese prototypes of feta, and cave-aged hard cheeses. Preservation of cheeses in brine, olive oil and by aging made it possible to ship products renown for quality from the colonies of Magna Grecia. Greek mastery of the seas spurred on prosperity as an exploding mainland population increasingly demanded quality goods.</p>



<p>Greek cheeses have had diverse uses for millennia. They continue to be central ingredients in sweet and savory dishes, pies and pastries. Hard cheeses are grated over other foods, while softer cheeses are crumbled over seafood, pasta and vegetable dishes. Cheese pies with layered, flaky dough (plakounta or plakous) go back to temple offerings, so phyllo, too, has ancient origins. Think about that connection to antiquity the next time you order a spanakopita!</p>



<p>Let’s set the record straight about feta. Domestic “feta” is usually made from cow’s milk. Cheese is rarely made from cow’s milk in Greece. Much of the land is unsuitable for pastoral grazing. Instead, the rocky terrain favors sheep and goats that clamber about, chowing down on the outcroppings of wild flowers, rogue grasses and brush. The local vegetation upon which the animals graze results in varied aroma and flavor notes. So authentic feta can be more complex than that mushy salt bomb on your salad.</p>



<p><strong>Back to Its Roots</strong></p>



<p>Although similar white, brined cheeses have been made in the Balkans and the Middle East for centuries, the European Union decreed that to qualify as feta, the cheese must be made in Greece. The ratios of sheep and goat milks can vary within limits, but the same basic recipe must be followed, regardless of whether it’s made in a home kitchen, small farm or industrial setting. Fetas vary. The two high-quality brands I sampled were quite distinct, even though both were the genuine articles, carrying the coveted European Union’s Protected Designation of Origin (or PDO). Feta, originally a sheep cheese, can contain up to 30% goat milk. A 70% sheep to 30% goat formulation seems the most popular. But some cheesemakers create an all sheep product while others offer an all “goat feta” with a qualifier on the label. Feta is soft, and you might mistake it as fresh cheese, but that isn’t exactly true. Once immersed in brine, the feta is left to cure from one to several months.</p>



<p>Where can you get authentic feta and other Greek cheeses? Astoria is a multi-ethnic neighborhood, famous for its Greek immigrant community, located in New York City’s borough of Queens. There are more authentic Greek restaurants or tavernas, bakeries and specialty stores in Astoria than anywhere else in the United States. And Astoria is home to Titan Foods, the largest retailer of Greek foods in North America. Want to find those impossible-to-find Greek cheeses? They’re right here. Don’t live in the New York area? Not to worry. Titan Foods ships anywhere in the United States.</p>



<p><strong>Sampling Feta</strong></p>



<p>To sample authentic Greek cheeses, I rode the LaGuardia Airport bound M60 bus across Central Harlem and got off the first stop after the Robert F. Kennedy (Triborough) Bridge to meet Anatoli “Anna” Mastoras, the director of marketing and public relations for Titan Foods. Anatoli is one of three American daughters involved in the family business founded in 1984 by her parents, Costas and Stavroula Mastoras. Costas and Stavroula immigrated from Thessaloniki Greece as graduate students in the 70’s. Costas was credited with introducing America to Greek yogurt in the 80’s. In 2001, the family launched an importing and distribution company, Optima Foods, formerly Titan Foods Imports. Optima supplies restaurants, supermarkets and gourmet shops throughout the United States and Canada.</p>



<p>Walking into Titan Foods, it was impossible to miss the display of bakery goods in front of the espresso machines. Mouth-watering, savory cheese pies and traditional pastries beckoned from refrigerated display windows. Titan’s bakery division is named for Costas&#8217; late mother Domna who was a baker. Early for my meeting with Anatoli, I had just enough time to snap some photos and purchase a few boxes of those irresistible cheese pies and sweet pastries.</p>



<p>Turning right at the baklava counter, I found the entire back section of the store contains what is probably the most impressive selection of imported Greek cheeses and olives anywhere in America. Nearby, rows of imported canned and packaged goods line shelf after shelf, while along a wall to the left, I found spices and herbs. Concluding my reconnaissance, it was time to meet Anatoli. We selected a variety of cheese for taste-testing at home, since COVID-19, sampling at the counters of any cheese shop has been suspended in New York.</p>



<p><strong>The Cheese</strong></p>



<p>Whereas many sheep cheeses from Spain and the Pyrenees can break down oily, the Greek remains well integrated and buttery. All the cheeses I sampled finished exceptionally well on a neutral note with no sharp or unpleasant aftertaste.</p>



<p><strong><u>Feta</u></strong></p>



<p>Some commentators note herbal, even white wine aromas. The more goat milk in the formula, the tangier the taste. I sampled fetas by Dodani and Arahova brands, both with 70/30 sheep vs. goat. For those who find the 70/30 too sharp or tangy, try an all sheep version. The 70/30 Feta by Dodoni had a light aroma, the flavor was refined, smooth, not sharp. The 70/30 by Arahova presented a more complex aroma, richer flavor, with tangy hints of buttermilk and yogurt. Unsurprisingly, both brands were salty. How salty? 303mg of sodium per 30 gram serving. For a soft white cheese with less sodium, try Manouri, a feta by-product that contains approximately 1/3 less sodium.</p>



<p><strong><u>Manouri (brand: Hotos)</u></strong></p>



<p>Delicate and elegant. This is a fresh whey cheese, smoother and creamier than feta, used in sweet and savory dishes, including spanakopita and phyllo pastries drizzled with honey</p>



<p>Aroma: mild, fresh, sweet grass</p>



<p>Flavor: mildly saline, a whisper of sheep, nothing sharp or tangy</p>



<p>Texture: tiny minced curds, more buttery than creamy</p>



<p>Finish: refreshing</p>



<p><strong><u>Graviera DOC (Mendiodakis)</u></strong></p>



<p>A semi-hard cheese made in Naxos and Crete (Kriti) aged three to five months. On Crete, made from ewe’s milk, sometimes goat. In Naxos, cow’s milk with ewe or goat. An all-around table cheese and an ingredient in pastries. Give it and all the semi-hard cheeses 30 minutes at room temperature before serving.</p>



<p>Aroma: sweet sheep butter</p>



<p>Flavor: sharp start, then sweet sheep with a tiny tang midway, not as salty as a Pecorino, nutty</p>



<p>Texture: similar to Gruyère, smooth then crumble turns dry with mild astringency</p>



<p>Finish: dry, astringency on tongue fades, leaves a whisper of pine nut</p>



<p><strong><u>Kaseri/Kasseri DOC (Orino)</u></strong></p>



<p>A semi-hard cheese made in Thessalia, Mitilini Island and Xanthis, aged 12 weeks. One of the most ancient cheeses.</p>



<p>It’s approximately 80% ewe’s, 20% goat milks, used as table cheese and for melting.</p>



<p>Aroma: mild, floral and herbal lurk under butter</p>



<p>Flavor: full bodied, sheepy-butter taste, yields to mild tang, well managed salinity</p>



<p>Texture: similar to a soft, springy cheddar, melts in the mouth, a touch of dryness</p>



<p>Finish: pleasing, slightly oily, bit of tang caresses the sides of the tongue and hard palate, perhaps least salty of the aged cheeses</p>



<p><strong><u>Kefalotyri DOC/ Livadi</u></strong></p>



<p>A hard cheese known since the Byzantine era, made from the whole milk of sheep or goats or both. Aged three to four months.</p>



<p>Aroma: woody, subdued butter notes</p>



<p>Flavor: salty and tangy, a whisper of goat although sheep dominates</p>



<p>Texture: firm, gummy, chewy, not melty</p>



<p>Finish: salty, particles remain firm, sticking to teeth, a long neutral finish</p>



<p><strong><u>Kefalograviera Metsovou (Vlaha)</u></strong></p>



<p>Aroma: buttery sheep</p>



<p>Flavor: first hit is salt, then fades to gummy butter, nutty midway</p>



<p>Texture: firm but gummy like the Kefalotyri</p>



<p>Finish: well integrated salt and toasted almond</p>



<p><strong><u>Smoked Metsovou (Vlaha)</u></strong></p>



<p>Smoked cheeses are rare outside Greece but Titan has them.</p>



<p>Aroma: strong wood smoke</p>



<p>Flavor: smoky</p>



<p>Texture: firmer than smoked mozzarella, pasty</p>



<p>Finish: forest fire, definitely an acquired taste</p>



<p><em>Other Well-Known Cheeses</em></p>



<p><strong><u>Myzithra</u></strong></p>



<p>An ancient ancestor of all whey cheeses. There are two types, fresh and unsalted, and aged.</p>



<p><strong><u>Galotiri DOC</u></strong></p>



<p>Another ancient fresh cheese often homemade from ewe’s milk. Aged from only a few days up to a few months.</p>



<p><strong><u>Anthotyros DOC</u></strong></p>



<p>A whey cheese (ewe, goat or both) with the addition of milk and cream, made in a fresh, soft form, for use in sweet and savory pastries. Can be aged up to 12 months as a hard cheese for grating. &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; CC</p>



<p class="has-medium-font-size">RECIPE</p>



<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>How to Make Traditional Saganaki</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="768" src="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/AdobeStock_14833811-1-1024x768.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-6177" srcset="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/AdobeStock_14833811-1-1024x768.jpeg 1024w, https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/AdobeStock_14833811-1-300x225.jpeg 300w, https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/AdobeStock_14833811-1-768x576.jpeg 768w, https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/AdobeStock_14833811-1-1536x1152.jpeg 1536w, https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/AdobeStock_14833811-1-2048x1536.jpeg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption><span class="media-credit">andrifoto &#8211; stock.adobe.com</span></figcaption></figure>



<p>Saganaki doesn’t refer to a cheese but the double-handled pan in which it is fried. Any small, cast iron pan is perfect for this simple recipe. The cheeses most commonly used are Graviera, Kefalograviera, or Kefalotyri. Use a semi-hard cheese cut thick enough to be fried on both sides without melting into a puddle.</p>



<p>Ingredients</p>



<p>•&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Cheese cut into 4 x 4 inches squares, between 1/2-2/3 of an inch thick</p>



<p>•&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; A tablespoon of olive oil</p>



<p>•&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; A dish of all-purpose flour&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>•&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Lemon wedges</p>



<p>Instructions:</p>



<p>1. Dip cheese in cold water to moisten, shake off excess.</p>



<p>2. Dredge the cheese in the flour, coating all sides.</p>



<p>3. Heat the olive oil in the frying pan over a medium heat.</p>



<p>4. When the oil just begins to sizzle, quickly place the flour-coated cheese in the pan.</p>



<p>5. Brown the bottom side of the cheese, then flip it over to brown the top. The sides should also be browned.</p>



<p>6. Serve with lemon wedges, nothing more.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/greek-cheese-cheese-connoisseur/">Greek Cheese:  It&#8217;s Not Just Feta</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com">Cheese Connoisseur</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Le fromage parfait pour cette saison !</title>
		<link>https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/perfect-oktoberfest-cheeses/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia McDonald Bennett]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Sep 2021 16:47:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Feature]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[German]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Oktoberfest]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/?p=6186</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A how-to on incorporating cheese into Oktoberfest celebrations. Oktoberfest celebrations—those cheerful, colorful odes to German beer and culture—kick off all over the world in September. Attendees at one of these events, whether they go to an official celebration in Munich or a smaller gathering in their community, can expect to find a specific style of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/perfect-oktoberfest-cheeses/">Perfect Oktoberfest Cheeses</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com">Cheese Connoisseur</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2>A how-to on incorporating cheese into Oktoberfest celebrations.</h2>



<p>Oktoberfest celebrations—those cheerful, colorful odes to German beer and culture—kick off all over the world in September. Attendees at one of these events, whether they go to an official celebration in Munich or a smaller gathering in their community, can expect to find a specific style of drink that can be found as soon as the weather starts to cool and leaves begin to fall. It’s known as Oktoberfest beer, and it’s a winner with cheeses of all kinds.</p>



<p>According to Christian DeBenedetti, author of “The Great American Ale Trail” and owner of <a href="https://www.wolvesandpeople.com">Wolves and People Farmhouse Brewery </a>in Newberg, OR, Oktoberfest beer is generally thought to have sprung out of a tradition started by the Bavarian royal family. “The first so-called Oktoberfest beer was served for a royal wedding, and Oktoberfest became an ongoing fall tradition in which a bolder, somewhat spicier offering of traditionally lighter German beers would emerge for the season,” he says. These beers tend to be a touch nuttier, hoppier, higher in alcohol and darker in color than the pale blond lagers that are often associated with Germany.</p>



<p>DeBenedetti called Oktoberfest quaffers “bountiful beer for bountiful occasions” and says brewers tend to stay true to the style when making them. “There’s no one recipe for Oktoberfest beer, and there’s certainly a lot of variation around the world. People also use Oktoberfest styles of beer as an inspiration. But there’s a lot of reverence for beer tradition, so it’s definitely not a style that strays widely.”</p>



<p>That being said, the narrow range of Oktoberfest-style beers does include a few lighter choices as well as darker ones. That means there is an option for nearly every beer lover in this category.</p>



<p>Festival goers at an Oktoberfest celebration can expect to find hot pretzels, sausages and other traditional German foods—but cheese makes an outstanding pairing, as well. “Cheese is a staple food in Bavaria,” DeBenedetti points out. The key is to find cheeses that complement the beers well, and not end up with combinations that overwhelm either the drink or the dairy product.</p>



<p>The good news is that there are several great options for that. Steve Jones, national sales director for <a href="https://farmsforcitykids.org">Spring Brook Farm</a> in Burnett, WI, believes Oktoberfest beers are some of the best drinks to serve with cheese. Beer has three main components that add flavor: hops, yeast and malt. Bitter hops can be hard to match to other flavors. Beer yeast can be easier to work with because its esters complement some cheeses.</p>



<p>“Malt is my favorite of the flavor components to work with because it’s easy to understand,” he says. “With malt, you get those grainy notes. In my mind, they’re a perfect pairing for cheese because cheese is basically a grain-based product, as cows are eating grains before they make the milk. There’s also a malty sweetness to Oktoberfest beers, and that makes it really easy for pairing. You don’t get that in a lot of beers out there, especially in this modern world of IPAs and sours and such.”</p>



<p>What cheeses, specifically, should make it onto the menu along with common Oktoberfest and other fall beer? There are several options based on the specific characteristics of the drinks at hand.</p>



<p><strong>Cheeses for Darker Beers</strong></p>



<p>In Jones’s mind, the darker, more copper-colored Oktoberfest beers are the “slam-dunk category” when finding cheeses that are a perfect match. His ideal pairing is an English farmstead cheese such as Cheshire, cloth-bound cheddar and Wensleydale.</p>



<p>“Comté and other Alpine cheeses are also going to work well with those beers,” he adds. Serve them with bratwurst or other German-style sausages, a sliced apple or a juicy pickle. “Pickles are really nice because they don’t distract and that little acidic hit is a nice counterbalance to the sweetness of beer.”</p>



<p>Another option for darker Oktoberfest beers is washed rind cheeses. “Try something with a little stinky funk to them,” Jones says. For that category, he likes Spring Brook Farm’s Morbier-style cheese. Called Ashbrook, it is made with raw Jersey cow milk and has a distinctive layer of vegetable ash running through the middle. It is aged for three months to give that pleasing bit of stink. Or serve up Nimble, a firm, mild cheese made with both goat and cow milk from <a href="https://www.boxcarrhandmadecheese.com">Boxcarr Handmade Cheese</a>, located in Cedar Grove, NC. Appropriately enough, it is washed with a mixture of local beer and brine.</p>



<p>“My number one recommendation for Oktoberfest drinking is Gouda,” says Michele Molier, manager of in-person events and education at New York City’s <a href="https://www.murrayscheese.com">Murray’s Cheese</a>. “Gouda tends to be a very kettle corn-style cheese, where you get the saltiness of the popcorn but the caramely flavor of caramel corn.”</p>



<p>Gouda, she continues, is an example of what’s known as a contrasting pairing. “There’s bitterness in the beer, and there’s sweetness in the Gouda, so you get two opposite things that line up nicely on the palate.” Although there are people who like that bit of bitterness, for others, “that slight touch of Gouda sweetness smooths out the beer’s bite.”</p>



<p>Murray’s has two Goudas that Molier believes are good choices with Oktoberfest beer. Its Estate Gouda has a nice mix of nuttiness, grassiness and richness, with some wheat and malted barley flavors that complement the flavors in the brews. Honey Goat Gouda combines honey and goat milk. The result is a creamy cheese with a warming sweetness and aromas of fresh hay. Both cheeses are made in The Netherlands, so they bring an old world flavor to the old-world spirit of Oktoberfest.</p>



<p>The opposite of a contrasting pairing is a resonance pairing, where similar flavors are paired together. “That’s where I would recommend cheddars,” says Molier. “Unlike Gouda, cheddars are salty and acidic and earthy, and that matches up well to the earthy bitterness of an Oktoberfest beer. I would go with a cloth-bound wheel of English cheddar over a domestic cheddar. English cheddars retain a lot of their earthy qualities like grassiness and maltiness.” <a href="https://www.montgomerycheese.co.uk">Montgomery’s Cheddar</a> is rubbed with lard before it&#8217;s wrapped in cloth to help the fabric stick. That extra layer of fat helps the cheese stands up to the rich beer.</p>



<p>Molly Browne, CCP, ACS CCSE, education manager for the Madison, WI-based <a href="https://www.wisconsindairy.org">Dairy Farmers of Wisconsin</a>, agrees that the robust, umami flavor of aged cheddar is an ideal pairing with dark, spicy Oktoberfest beer (although she recommends adding a dollop of grainy mustard to the cheese to give it a little more kick).</p>



<p>For people whose thoughts turn to German-style beers with German-style cheeses rather than specifically Oktoberfest-style drinks in the fall, she has been a proponent of drinking Hefeweizen with brick cheese, the Wisconsin original that has been popularized by its use in Detroit-style pizza. It was invented by Swiss immigrant John Jossi, who worked at a Limburger plant after moving to the United States. “He knew Americans tended to have a more mild palate for cheese, so he wanted to make a less pungent version of Limburger,” Browne says. Sometimes referred to as the “married man’s Limburger,” the cheese has a lightly nutty and mild flavor with nice acidity. As it ripens, it takes on some of the pungency of its famously stinky cousin.</p>



<p>“To me, brick cheese pairs really beautifully with wheat beer,” says Browne. “Hefeweizen tends to be on the more floral side, and you can get some nice fruity nuance in those beers. That picks up on the more delicate notes that come through in brick.”</p>



<p>Browne is a proponent of the term “what grows together goes together.” Plus, she says, Germans have a very specific palate that is expressed in both their cheeses and beer. Keeping that in mind, she has a few thoughts on pairing beer and cheeses that have their origin in the European nation.</p>



<p>Butterkäse is perhaps the most ubiquitous cheese in Germany. It is a very mild, buttery, high fat content cheese that is quite creamy. It’s often called a table cheese because people will leave it sitting on the table, where it can easily be sliced, spread or used in cooking on a whim. Her recommendation is to enjoy it with Kölsch.</p>



<p>“Kölsch is very sessionable,” says Browne. “When you think about pairing, you want to consider the intensity of each item you’re pairing. You wouldn’t want to pair a really mild beer with a really pungent style of cheese.” Since Butterkäse and Kölsch are both quite mild, one won’t overwhelm the other.</p>



<p>In addition, the effervescence of Kölsch makes it perfect with this buttery cheese. “With a creamy, high fat content cheese, those bubbles are going to have a really nice palate cleansing effect. It’s going to refresh your palate and keep it ready for next bite,” Browne says. Americans who struggle to find the German version of butterkäse can look for ones made in Wisconsin.</p>



<p>Belgian ale is an ideal pairing for it is another well-known German cheese: Limburger. Belgian ales tend to have a bit of funk to them, which complements the famously stinky cheese nicely. Don’t be put off by the smell, Browne reminds those who are less familiar with Limburger. “The flavor can actually be really delicate mild and lean on the more meaty spectrum than the gross spectrum. Its bark is worse than its bite.” Common food pairings with Limburger, including summer sausage and onion jam, make sense for a fall or Oktoberfest spread.Browne has another less conventional recommendation, too. “Strawberry jam on the Limburger puts such a unique and interesting spin on that cheese. There’s just enough sweet and savory in the pairing that it surprises your palate in a good way.”</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/perfect-oktoberfest-cheeses/">Perfect Oktoberfest Cheeses</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com">Cheese Connoisseur</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Pour la parade espagnoule le fromage de la perfectionne !</title>
		<link>https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/manchego-cheese-connoisseur/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Hannah Howard]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 Sep 2021 17:47:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Feature]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[manchego]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spain]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/?p=6181</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This cheese from Spain has widespreadappeal due to its rich, bold flavor. Manchego is simply iconic. It’s nearly impossible to think of Spanish cheese without this sheep’s milk wheel springing immediately to mind. Manchego hails from the provinces of Albacete, Ciudad Real, Cuenca and Toledo in Castile-La Mancha in central Spain, a region of lush [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/manchego-cheese-connoisseur/">Manchego: Spanish Pride, Universal Deliciousness</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com">Cheese Connoisseur</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>This cheese from Spain has widespread<br>appeal due to its rich, bold flavor.</strong></p>



<p>Manchego is simply iconic. It’s nearly impossible to think of Spanish cheese without this sheep’s milk wheel springing immediately to mind. Manchego hails from the provinces of Albacete, Ciudad Real, Cuenca and Toledo in Castile-La Mancha in central Spain, a region of lush pastures dotted with castles and windmills <em>a la</em> Don Quixote. (Cervantes wrote about Manchego in his “Don Quixote of La Mancha,” so it’s a cheese with literary credentials).</p>



<p>Manchego is flavorful yet absolutely approachable, a great choice for cheese newbies and experts alike. It has a briny tartness, beautifully balanced by an undercurrent of sweetness. Depending on the season, the wheel and the maker, it might have sweet notes of caramel or honey or a piquant, gamey spiciness. (Cheese­mongers I spoked with laughed that many seem to think the cheese is pronounced “Man-chen-go,” inserting a second “n” that doesn’t belong.)</p>



<p>Made from the milk of Manchega sheep, Manchego is one of the most beloved Spanish exports. Archaeologists have found evidence that dates cheesemaking in the La Mancha region to as far back as the Bronze Age. The traditional methods of producing Manchego have been preserved with a Protected Designation of Origin (PDO) since 1984. The exterior of the wheels sport a telltale basketweave rind, made from the grass molds that press into the rind as Manchego matures and made to evoke the imprint of traditional esparto molds.</p>



<p>“Manchego accounts for about a third of the production of Spain’s cheese,” says Lydia Burns, founder of the cheese consulting company Savvy Squirrel Consulting. Burns also works for the boutique cheese importer <a href="https://www.rogerscollection.us">Rogers Collection</a> in Yarmouth, ME, and teaches cheese education to culinary school students. The cheese is especially “emblematic and cool because Spain is the only traditional cheese­making country from Europe where the majority of production is not from cow’s milk.”</p>



<p>Sheep’s milk gives Manchego much of its characteristic richness and bold flavor. On average, sheep&#8217;s milk is 7.4% butterfat compared to 3.7% for cow’s milk and 3.6% for goat’s milk. It also contains more lactose and minerals than either. “Sheep’s milk cheeses have a great supple texture because of their higher fat and casein content,” Burns explains. “There are tangy, light flavors in lactic younger cheeses, and then a more intense flavor as it ages, with rich notes of olive oil. The flavor of the milk itself really stands out.”</p>



<p>Like Parmigiano Reggiano in Italy or Gruyère in the Swiss Alps, Manchego cheese carries with it a sense of deeply rooted tradition and regional identity and pride.</p>



<p><strong>It All Starts with the Sheep</strong></p>



<p>Manchega sheep, who we can thank for Manchego, are native to the La Mancha plateau in New Castile. They are white and black and often a combination of both colors. Their ancestors were called <em>Ovis aries ligeries</em>, and these sheep migrated across the Pyrenees and much of northern Spain before finally settling in La Mancha, where they were domesticated and bred for their milk. La Mancha’s terrain is too rugged for cows, but it’s perfect for sheep to thrive, especially manchegas.</p>



<p>“Sheep are hard to raise, and don’t make a lot of milk,” says Burns. “In Spain, the local breed is subsidized by the government. A major ingredient is time: over many years, the manchega sheep have been bred for productivity.”</p>



<p>“Manchego is a full-bodied, rich, flavorful and highly approachable cheese,” says Jen Lopez, an account manager at <a href="https://www.forevercheese.com">Forever Cheese</a>, Astoria, NY. “Because of its rise in popularity over the last year, more Manchego is available than ever before.”</p>



<p>“Not all Manchego is created equal,” Lopez explains. Although PDO regulates many rules for the cheese’s production, there is still room for differences and nuances among producers, from the size of their operation to what they feed their sheep. The finest cheese is often made when the milk is richest, between August and December. At over 30,000 square miles, the region for making Manchego is huge, and microclimates within the areas make for wheels with distinct flavor profiles and personalities. Some makers coat their rinds with wax or other protective substances (others don’t); some use raw milk while many use pasteurized; and production can be automated or done by hand.</p>



<p>Age is a huge factor, too. Younger varieties have a “mild but pleasant full mouthfeel,” according to Burns. In these relatively fresh cheeses, the taste of the milk really shines through. Over months of careful aging, “savory, deep olive oil flavors emerge.”</p>



<p>In Spain, wheels of Manchego are sold according to their age, ranging from semicurado (three weeks to four months), curado (three to six months), and añejo or viejo (one to two years). In the U.S., Manchego is usually categorized by its age in months (easier for us to understand!).</p>



<p>Forever Cheese imports a wide variety of Manchego, including a wheel aged for six months called Chisquero. It’s a farmstead cheese (it uses milk from its own herd to craft the cheese) from a family farm in Ciudad Real that has been raising sheep for more than 200 years. A herd of 3,000 sheep live on the farm, which is run by solar energy. Cheesemaker Gabriel is part of the fifth generation of the Melgarejo family that owns the farm. He makes his signature Manchego Chisquero with raw Manchega sheep’s milk, rubbing the rind in olive oil. It has a supple, buttery flavor with a tangy finish.</p>



<p>Manchego Corcuera is made by the Corcuera family in La Puebla de Montalban, a small town just 20 minutes from Toledo. Its cheese is crafted from fresh milk the same day, and it’s aged for three months. The cheese boasts a fantastic butteriness and well-rounded, clean flavor of the sheep’s milk. <a href="http://www.corcuera.com">Quesos Corcuera</a> spans three generations of the Corcuera family. It all started with Eusebio and Julia, then their sons Ramon and Carlos took over; their sister Carmen and her niece Patricia are currently in charge. The family was instrumental in helping to create the DOP for Manchego in 1985. From a tiny house to a full-on factory, the operation has expanded over the generations but retains its commitment to fine craft and tradition.</p>



<p>The Rogers Collection imports a raw milk Manchego from Pasamontes Manchego, from the milk of five local shepherded flocks, and it is aged for a year. They graze on wild juniper, lavender, rosemary and thyme. Made from raw milk, this wheel is on another level of complexity with a long-lingering finish. Cheesemaker M. Dolores Palomares is the fourth generation in her family to carry on the shepherding and cheesemaking tradition—her great grandmother started the dairy. The cheese has deep flavors of hay and allspice, and is a beautiful testament to the possibilities of Manchego.</p>



<p><strong>The Tapas Tradition</strong></p>



<p>Manchego is often enjoyed as a part of a tapas spread, and you’ll see it in bars and restaurants from Madrid to New York City. Tapas originated as a bar snack to accompany wine and satisfy diners before Spain’s famously late dinnertime. The ritual of tapas dates back hundreds of years. It can be as simple as some bites of cheese and ham or a whole elaborate spread of small plates.</p>



<p>In bars around Spain, marinated Manchego sits on counters ready to be devoured. Oftentimes, Manchego is sliced and enjoyed as-is, perhaps with some crusty bread, olives, Marcona almonds and a glass of juicy Tempranillo. The nutty richness of Manchego makes it great for pairing with wine. Other great drinks to savor with Manchego include crisp dry whites such as Albarino or Vermentino, or bubbly Cava, which cuts through the cheese’s buttery mouthfeel. A single-malt whiskey can stand up to the savory, big flavors of an aged Manchego.</p>



<p>Membrillo, a firm, sweet-tart quince paste is a classic accompaniment for Manchego. “It’s perfect because it’s sweet but not cloyingly sweet,” explains Lopez. “The bit of acidity from pectin and quince reacts perfectly with the fattiness of the cheese.”</p>



<p>Other times, Manchego may be incorporated into recipes. It can be melted with dates, skewered with roasted pimento peppers, melted atop meatballs or even fried. “There’s been a real Manchego shortage during the pandemic,” says Lopez. “People’s purchasing habits changed, and sales exploded in the U.S. and Europe. We’re waiting for cheese to age. We still can’t see the end of that tunnel yet—we don’t know yet when we’ll be all caught up, and we will be experiencing that for quite some time.”</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/manchego-cheese-connoisseur/">Manchego: Spanish Pride, Universal Deliciousness</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com">Cheese Connoisseur</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Eblouissant ;)</title>
		<link>https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/fog-lights-cypress-grove-cheese-connoisseur/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lisa White]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 Sep 2021 17:02:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Centerfold Cheeses]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cypress Grove]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fog Lights]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[soft-ripened]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/?p=6170</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Arcata, CA-based Cypress Grove, launched Fog Lights, its newest addition to the award-winning Humboldt Fog family of cheeses, last summer in response to a rapidly changing market. “We heard our customers&#8217; need for retail-ready, grab-and-go cheeses, and we rallied our teams to develop and launch Fog Lights in just a few short months,” says Janne [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/fog-lights-cypress-grove-cheese-connoisseur/">Cypress Grove:  Fog Lights</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com">Cheese Connoisseur</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Arcata, CA-based <a href="https://www.cypressgrovecheese.com">Cypress Grove</a>, launched Fog Lights, its newest addition to the award-winning Humboldt Fog family of cheeses, last summer in response to a rapidly changing market.</p>



<p>“We heard our customers&#8217; need for retail-ready, grab-and-go cheeses, and we rallied our teams to develop and launch Fog Lights in just a few short months,” says Janne Rasmussen, Cypress Grove’s marketing manager. “We were able to flip the lights on quickly by capitalizing on some of the innovation already achieved during our Little Giant product trials, which was still in development at the time, and apply them to Fog Lights.”</p>



<p>Introduced in March of this year, Little Giant is a bloomy goat cheese described as smooth, buttery and delicate. This bright, fudgy cheese has subtly sweet, yeast-like flavors reminiscent of bread fresh out of the oven, along with mushroomy notes that intensify as the cheese ages. Its downy-white rind is edible, similar to a brie, and Little Giant continues to ripen from the outside in as it ages.</p>



<p>When Fog Lights was first developed around 2010, Cypress Grove hadn&#8217;t yet cracked the code on small format soft-ripened cheese moisture control throughout shelf life, and it was discontinued soon after.</p>



<p>“Over a decade has passed since then, and we have run many trials and stumbled upon a few innovations along the way; we were able to apply those learnings to Fog Lights, along with a fine-tuned recipe,” Rasmussen says. “Many trials later for different items, we were happy to re-introduce an improved and reimagined version of the Fog Lights.”</p>



<p>The name Fog Lights is a connection to Humboldt Fog, Cypress Grove’s flagship soft-ripened cheese that is sold as a 5-pound wheel. However, this cheese is quite demure in size compared to Humboldt Fog, clocking in at only 6 ounces.</p>



<p>“So, the name Fog Lights felt appropriate to make a connection to Humboldt Fog while playing with the cheese&#8217;s petite size,” Rasmussen says.</p>



<p>It has a similar flavor profile to Humboldt Fog — bright and citrusy, but a bit earthier and more dense and fudgy. Also similar to its namesake, Fog Lights is ash covered and mold ripened, but because of its small size, Fog Lights does not have the classic ribbon of black ash through its center.</p>



<p>Fog Lights is best paired with sundried tomatoes and a fresh baguette, then washed down with Sauvignon Blanc or an IPA.</p>



<p>“We also love Fog Lights with Castelvetrano olives, seeded crackers, sparkling wine and, if we&#8217;re being honest, just a fork,” Rasmussen says. “Its small size also makes it a perfect cheese for topping a salad, soup or crostini with a small wedge for a big impact.” It is is available in limited distribution nationwide as well as through Cypress Grove’s online store.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/fog-lights-cypress-grove-cheese-connoisseur/">Cypress Grove:  Fog Lights</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com">Cheese Connoisseur</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Créer à partir de nos erreurs !</title>
		<link>https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/inspired-cheeseboards-cheese-connoisseur/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Carol Bareuther]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 Sep 2021 16:55:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Feature]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cheeseboards]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/?p=6166</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>You don’t have to be an expert to getcreative with cheese presentations. Say the words ‘cheese and crackers’ and fond memories often come to mind. Maybe it’s of one of Grandma’s wooden plates set with bite-sized squares of tooth-picked cheddar, or a baseball size pecan-crusted pimento cheese ball, or a red waxed Gouda with a [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/inspired-cheeseboards-cheese-connoisseur/">Crafting an Inspired Cheeseboard</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com">Cheese Connoisseur</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>You don’t have to be an expert to get<br>creative with cheese presentations.</p>



<p>Say the words ‘cheese and crackers’ and fond memories often come to mind. Maybe it’s of one of Grandma’s wooden plates set with bite-sized squares of tooth-picked cheddar, or a baseball size pecan-crusted pimento cheese ball, or a red waxed Gouda with a party-starting wedge already carved, each surrounded by crackers and served before holiday meals. Or maybe it’s of a 1980s-era lunchbox when this combo became conveniently cool paired with ham, turkey and even cookies under brand names like Lunchables.</p>



<p>Recently, however, pairing cheese with other ingredients has undergone an upscaling. Images of artfully-arranged cheeseboards, and sister fare such as charcuterie platters, have taken social media by storm receiving as many or more ‘likes’ as those of movie stars. Today, building these edible works of art may inspire more trepidation rather than anticipation. Relax, say the experts. It’s not that difficult to create inspired cheeseboards for everyday and special occasions.</p>



<p>“When it comes to building a cheeseboard, in my opinion, there are no rules,” says Nat Belkov, the design lead and creative content manager for <a href="https://www.murrayscheese.com">Murray’s Cheese</a>, a New York-headquartered artisanal cheese and specialty foods wholesaler and retailer. “I try to think outside of the box and encourage our customers to do the same. There&#8217;s no way to know that something doesn&#8217;t work as a pairing until you try. Often, you&#8217;ll discover something you never would&#8217;ve dreamed would work so well together. And what&#8217;s more pleasurable than sharing an experience like that—or a new discovery—with those you love?!”</p>



<p>THE BASICS</p>



<p>Here are six basic tips to build an innovative cheeseboard.</p>



<p><strong>1. Select the cheese or cheeses.</strong></p>



<p>“I recommend choosing a variety of cheeses either based on texture (hard, soft, fresh, bloomy rind) or based on a variety of milks (cows, goat, sheep, etc.). Three types of cheeses are the perfect number if you’re entertaining,” says Grilled Cheese Social blogger, MacKenzie Smith, a two-time <a href="https://www.foodnetwork.com">Food Network</a> champion, cookbook author, cheese expert and executive chef based in New Smyrna Beach, FL.</p>



<p>Or take a different approach. Perhaps highlight a region in France like the Loire Valley by featuring a flight of soft-ripened goat&#8217;s milk cheeses with various rind formations and textures, suggests Jessica Sennett, a cheese specialist and Brooklyn, NY-based brainchild behind the <a href="https://cheesegrotto.com">Cheese Grotto</a>, a device that extends the life of cheeses by acting like a mini cheese cave. “Or source cheeses that pair best with beer: a clothbound cheddar, a funky semi-firm washed rind and a blue.”</p>



<p>Know your audience. Understand what’s too funky for some folks or on the other hand, where some folks might want to step outside the box a bit and be more daring.</p>



<p>“Maybe choose something sensorially soft — Chabichou Du Poitou from the Deux-Sevres region of France for the minerally luscious and lactic goat lovers, button mushroom and churned butter-like Robiola Bosina for double cream brie lovers looking to try something different, or the deceptively approachable and supremely smooth Brebirousse d&#8217;Argental for a pop of carrot-orange color on your board,” says Murray’s Cheese’s Belkov. “Or go to the other end of the spectrum in terms of texture and even taste. Opt for salty-sweet Romano, oniony funky Scharfe Maxx Extra, deeply savory Montgomery&#8217;s Cheddar from Neal&#8217;s Yard or Grafton&#8217;s toasty caramel-like Shepsog for those that love a crystalline crunch.”</p>



<p><strong>2. Choose the ideal type and number of accompaniments.</strong></p>



<p>Belkov of Murray’s Cheese, for example, likes to have at least one or two charcuterie items on a board when sharing with three to five people, unless his guests are averse to meat. For the most approachable board, he selects a hard salami like Genoa, Soppressata or Calabrese and slices it thin before arranging it on the board. Beyond that, salty Prosciutto di Parma, peppery Speck, and Bresaola or Culatello and Iberico are ideal for those not afraid of the more complex pork and decadently rich flavors inherent to these crafted cured meats.</p>



<p>Beyond this, Belkov recommends at least one pantry-based pairing item per cheese on the board. Crackers and hunks of baguette are great vehicles, so choosing a universally enjoyed one will bode well for the entirety of the board. Having at least one pickled item is always wise to serve as a palate cleanser, plus the acid balances richer-tasting cheeses and meats. Cornichons and olives are the universal workhorses of a cheeseboard, but wilder choices like pickled piquillo peppers, carrots, asparagus or other pickled vegetables and antipasti work well, too.</p>



<p>Though superabundant, intricately set cheeseboards can be a feast for the eyes, they may not be the most realistic version of what someone can routinely make in a home kitchen on a daily or weekly basis, says the Cheese Grotto’s Sennett. “As cheese experts don’t want to relegate cheeseboards solely to special occasions, having one accompaniment per cheese is a great rule of thumb. It&#8217;s also good to select three accompaniments that will bring out different characteristics in the different cheese types on the board. This is so that as they are plated alongside each other, there is room to explore.”</p>



<p><strong>3. Mix sweet and savory items in the tastiest way.</strong></p>



<p>For instance, roasted or salted nuts and dried fruits can complement a variety of cheeses so they&#8217;re always a safe bet. Savory spreads and chutneys such as roasted tomato jam, red wine-stewed onions or artichoke spread complement milder cheeses. Sweeter jams are a great addition to a board that includes goat cheese, certain blues, or even, in the case of apple butter, a good savory-sweet cheddar.</p>



<p>“If I’m mixing sweet and savory accompaniments on one board, I will often feature one sweet item, one sweet-savory item (like a tomato and white sultana chutney from Le Bon Magot) and one fully savory item like Dequmana olives. The three accompaniments will facilitate the spectrum of a tasting experience on a board. Fresh fruit, like citrus, can also help tie together sweet and savory components on a board,” adds Sennett.</p>



<p><strong>4. Consider decorative accompaniments.</strong></p>



<p>The finishing touch of fresh herbs, for example, speaks to the agricultural landscape of cheesemaking and gives any cheeseboard both a fresh and finished feel. This might be a small sprig of thyme added to elevate a soft-ripened goat cheese.</p>



<p>“Flowers are a huge trend right now, but I always get concerned when I see carnations or other flowers that are sprayed with pesticides and other chemicals on a cheeseboard and touching the food that you’re about to eat. With that said, unless it’s edible flowers from a known source, I always stay stick with fresh herbs,” says Smith of Grilled Cheese Social.</p>



<p><strong>5. Place cheeses and other ingredients ideally on the board.</strong></p>



<p>The Cheese Grotto’s Sennett plates cheeses first, from left to right or clockwise, in the order of intensity. Though a cheeseboard can be enjoyed from any angle, she says, thinking of the tasting order of the cheeses is a great way to start. She then plates the accompaniments alongside the cheese for which makes the best pairing. Using nuts and nicely folded charcuterie in a river-like effect along the board to tie all the elements together is a great trick. Having smaller ramekins for honeys, jams and olives can help define the overall look of the board.</p>



<p>“Cheese tastes best when served at room temperature. So, you can set up your cheeseboard in advance, if desired, wrap it and refrigerate. Then take it out of the refrigerator an hour before serving. This also makes hard cheeses easier to cut. Although cheeses such as brie or Gouda slice best when chilled,” says Michael Landis, an American Cheese Society Certified Cheese Professional, food and beverage educator, author, TV news cheese expert and owner of Michael Landis LLC, in Lutz, FL.</p>



<p><strong>6. The board need not be a board.</strong></p>



<p>“We often teach private virtual cheeseboard classes at Cheese Grotto, and we encourage folks to use what they have: butcher paper, cutting board, a plate, a round board, a long board. Part of the fun of building a board is to explore different surfaces. One of our top teachers built a cheeseboard on stones from the perimeter of a lake to make a ripe wheel look like a waterfall. So, my advice here is to not limit your creativity,” says Sennett.</p>



<p><strong>SPECIAL OCCASION IDEAS</strong></p>



<p>Take the basics above and tweak them to build themed cheeseboards for seasonal and special occasions.</p>



<p>“There has recently been an emergence of cheeseboards pre-built into Tupperware that are ideal for picnics and tailgating,” says Cheese Grotto’s Sennett. “The main challenge is to make sure items don&#8217;t get jostled in transit, so the accompaniments must be able to fit compactly into the storage receptacle. We recently built a Tupperware cheeseboard with Vermont Creamery Bijou, Stag cheddar, olives, strawberries, salami Milano roses and Raincoast Crisps.”</p>



<p>For a Halloween Board, Murray’s Cheese’s Belkov recommends playfully pairing lowbrow and highbrow chocolates and other confections with a fudge-like Point Reyes Blue Cheese or crunchy caramelly Mimolette.</p>



<p>Or, for winter gatherings, Belkov adds, opt for snowy white cheeses like double creme brie, Fromager D&#8217;Affinois, La Tur or St. Marks and build a board with fruit jams, rye crackers, roasted walnuts or pecans, and chocolate-covered almonds. Style it with rosemary sprigs, sage leaves, cinnamon sticks and halved pomegranates that bare their juicy seeds like jewels embedded in the fruit.</p>



<p>Celebrate summer in winter or a destination nuptial with a wow-type of cheeseboard akin to what Smith created a few years ago. “It was for a ‘local Florida’ themed wedding. We made huge grazing tables with local cheeses, Florida-based honeys, fruits, Bradley’s Country sausage from Tallahassee, locally-made crackers and more! It had boiled peanuts, pickled okra, satsuma oranges and so many other great treats that are entirely from Florida. It was amazing and shows the endless creativity possible with a cheeseboard.”        </p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/inspired-cheeseboards-cheese-connoisseur/">Crafting an Inspired Cheeseboard</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com">Cheese Connoisseur</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>P'tit maiiiis ! Aerien OwO</title>
		<link>https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/la-femme-du-fromage-cheese-connoisseur/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lisa White ]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 Sep 2021 16:02:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Retailer Profile]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[La Femme du Fromage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orlando]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[retailer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/?p=6163</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Orlando’s La Femme du Fromage has become the go-to for artisan and hard-to-find cheeses. Big things do come in small packages. That is definitely true for Orlando’s La Femme du Fromage. Although only encompassing 212 square feet, what this cut-to-order cheese shop lacks in size it makes up for in its diverse offerings. While chains [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/la-femme-du-fromage-cheese-connoisseur/">A Small and Mighty Venture</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com">Cheese Connoisseur</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2>Orlando’s La Femme du Fromage has become the go-to for artisan and hard-to-find cheeses.</h2>



<p>Big things do come in small packages. That is definitely true for Orlando’s <a href="https://www.lafemmedufromage.com">La Femme du Fromage</a>. Although only encompassing 212 square feet, what this cut-to-order cheese shop lacks in size it makes up for in its diverse offerings.</p>



<p>While chains such as <a href="https://www.publix.com">Publix</a> and <a href="https://www.wholefoodsmarket.com">Whole Foods Market</a> may carry a Comté, it won’t be the 18-month aged version carried at La Femme du Fromage, which owner/president Tonda Corrente sourced from a personal contact in France. She also works directly with farms and their owners and will often pick up cheese shipments right from the airport.</p>



<p>“I work directly with producers like <a href="https://deercreekcheese.com">Deer Creek Creamery</a> and <a href="https://baetjefarms.com">Baetje Farms</a> and have suppliers in Wisconsin and France who send me hard-to-find cheeses,” she says. “There is a ton of representation around the country of things I can’t find down here, and those are the creameries I’m trying to source out to create a diverse cheese case.”</p>



<p>What also sets La Femme du Fromage apart is its educated staff, who will order unique cheeses upon request.</p>



<p>“I have people who travel to my store because I’m the only one of my kind,” Corrente says. “We want to represent what we can [with regional cheeses as well as imports].”</p>



<p><strong>From Wine to Cheese</strong></p>



<p>Corrente fell into the cheese industry by way of wine.</p>



<p>“I got into wine when I was in my early 20s and working in different restaurants and food outlets,” she explains. “I understood that my check average would triple if I knew how to sell wine, and then I started to fall in love with it.”</p>



<p>Corrente went on to work in higher-end restaurants that she felt had decent chefs and great wine lists. This expanded her knowledge of wine and food pairing.</p>



<p>“I wanted to learn why certain dishes sing with wine and about the relationship between food and wine,” she says. “It became my thing, and I loved orchestrating guests’ dining experience.”</p>



<p>This quickly set Corrente apart from others, while also being financially lucrative.</p>



<p>It was in 2006 when, at a low point in her life and without a job, she fell into helping others cook for parties.</p>



<p>“I actually taught myself how to cook and cater, because I love to host, entertain and pair food and wine,” she says. “This side gig helped me financially during a dark time in my life.”</p>



<p>Around this time, a new wine shop was opening in the area that was incorporating cheese.</p>



<p>“I went in to inquire about job opportunities and may have sounded like I was more educated than I was,” Corrente recalls. “They saw my resume and that I had been doing some catering, so assumed I had a culinary background. I really didn’t, as for me it was more about wine, but they still wanted me to help develop their cheese program.”</p>



<p>She underestimated her skills. Corrente had been studying wine for more than a decade at that time and was at the beginning of her foray into the cheese world.</p>



<p>“When you love wine and fall in love with food, then cheese is right around the corner,” she says. “When you start learning about cheese through the back end with your palate, it’s a different ballgame. It opened up a new world for me.”</p>



<p>Corrente says her new obsession was not just the relationship between regions, cheesemakers and styles but how cheese relates to wine. She became fascinated by how wine flavors change when introducing different cheeses and what happens when a pairing goes wrong.</p>



<p>As she continued her cheese and wine journey, Corrente not only refined her pairings, but, in 2008, started teaching classes to share her knowledge with others.</p>



<p>In 2012, Corrente visited Max McCalman, American cheese expert, author and the first Maître Fromager in a North American restaurant. He also spearheaded the creation of the Artisanal Bistro and Artisanal Premium Cheese Center and is an advocate for raw-milk cheeses.</p>



<p>“I went to Max’s cheese class in New York City, sat with him and showed him my pairing book,” Corrente says. “He came to Orlando a couple months later and joined me at one of my classes so he could see what I did here.”</p>



<p>Corrente recalls a ride with McCalman back from Disney, where he told her rather than be a minnow in New York, Los Angeles or one of the hot cheese areas, that she could be a shark in Orlando.</p>



<p>“It was almost one year to that day when I opened my cheese shop in Orlando,” she says. “When we had our grand opening, I flew Max down here so he could open our event space. He sold out a wine and cheese class with over 100 people; Max helped me put my flag in the ground.”</p>



<p><strong>A Leap of Faith</strong></p>



<p>Corrente’s public profile and expertise were what propelled her opportunity.</p>



<p>In January 2013, she was doing publicity at <a href="https://www.disney.com">Disney </a>and a local Fox affiliate, which garnered her coverage in local papers. It was during this time that John Rife, the owner of a new Orlando food hall, <a href="https://eastendmkt.com">East End Marke</a>t, was gathering a collection of entrepreneurs to open stalls in his site.</p>



<p>“He wanted to establish a food hall/public market like Seattle’s <a href="https://pikeplacemarket.org">Pike Place Market</a>, which would be the first of its kind in the Southeast,” Corrente explains. “When John created this, he knew he wanted certain things represented. He looked to see who could do cheese, and my name kept popping up in his search.”</p>



<p>When Rife initially reached out, Corrente thought he was asking her to help run someone else’s store. The thought of opening up her own business was not at all on her radar.</p>



<p>“I remember thinking I have no money, how would this work? How do I come up with financing?” she recalls. “John told me not to worry about the money, that it would come.”</p>



<p>Corrente was able to figure it out, financing used pieces of equipment, taking on a small overhead and starting with one tiny 8-foot cheese case. It obviously was a recipe for success; this October, La Femme du Fromage will celebrate its eighth year in business.</p>



<p>“It really changed my whole life,” Corrente says. “I went from being in the worst place I’ve been in my life emotionally to this miraculous journey; cheese saved my life.”</p>



<p>Yet, it wasn’t easy at first, as Corrente admits she was still pretty green in the industry. Although she had tasted and experienced a lot when it came to cheese, she had no business experience in terms of opening and running a retail store.</p>



<p>“How do you go into business without taking a college course?” she says. “Well, I taught myself how to be a cheesemonger, wine expert and chef, so I asked for help along the way to perfect my game. If you have the right attitude, you can’t go wrong.”</p>



<p><strong>Getting Up and Running</strong></p>



<p>From the start, Corrente carried cheeses she could acquire through a local distribution chain.</p>



<p>“Our distribution ability with purveyors opened up with the cheese explosion,” she says. “We were seeing a lot more availability.”</p>



<p>Initially, it was the Disney chefs that were her biggest customers, as she was the only high-end cheese shop in the area. But Corrente had to get creative when attracting other customers, setting herself apart from Whole Foods and other chains.</p>



<p>“COVID impacted everything, as local grocery chains have more buying power and can secure better deals than I can,” she says. “They also have other means to support their stores, so can take less margins. It has been a challenge for sure.”</p>



<p>Corrente says her “ammo” has been to constantly source cheeses that are hard to find by working directly with purveyors and artisan creameries.</p>



<p>“I’m working with people who can find me things I can special order, like seasonal items to survive this game,” she says. “But being the only cheese shop in Orlando for eight years with a reputation prior to starting, I have cemented myself in here in a way that people value my opinion and what I bring to the table.”</p>



<p>Surprisingly, even though space couldn’t be tighter, La Femme du Fromage offers an impressive cheese-centric menu of prepared foods. In addition to charcuterie boards and boxes, it includes croissant breakfast sandwiches, a variety of grilled cheese and other sandwiches, salads and flatbread pizza. The store has a Grilled Cheese Happy Hour every Friday and weekly pairings with sandwiches and beer.</p>



<p>“We work with a local French bakery to source our bread and include its French macarons for a pop of color and sweet treat with our charcuterie boxes,” Corrente says. “We also make jams and pickled vegetables and fruit.”</p>



<p>Corrente estimates that 35% to 40% of her business is catering, and she also does classes and collaborations with area chefs.</p>



<p>While some items are prepared in the food hall’s community kitchen, part of the store’s very limited square footage is dedicated to a hot line with an oven for preparing flatbreads and toasting sandwiches, a griddle for grill cheeses and a hot plate to heat up mac and cheese.</p>



<p>Despite its name, La Femme du Fromage is not exclusively a cheese purveyor; the shop includes a wide range of specialty food and beverages, from truffles to sangria.</p>



<p>With production space at a premium, there is not much room for retail. During COVID, one of the food hall spaces became available, and Corrente jumped at the chance to expand.</p>



<p>“This gave me a back storage room, so I could have everything at one site and under one roof, rather than utilizing an off-site storage facility,” she says. “Now, we have a room in the back as well as upstairs.”</p>



<p>This past March, Corrente turned the upstairs space into a vintage store, La Boutique. While some of the items pertain to food, like cheese boards, cheese knives and tea towels, there also are things like jewelry and homemade soap.</p>



<p>About two years ago, Corrente took the plunge and began construction on a new full-service restaurant that will be separate from the store.</p>



<p>“I was elbow deep in new restaurant construction when COVID hit, and I am 100% financially committed,” she says.</p>



<p>At press time, the restaurant was 80% completed. It will be located in downtown Orlando and includes a wine and cheese tapas bar with a lounge. Corrente describes it as having an “Old World style vibe”.</p>



<p>Her story is inspiring, and advice is even more so. “I’m giving a footprint for someone else to do this, too, especially rebuilding and rebalancing post-COVID,&#8221; Corrente advises. “Figure out what you want to do with your life and go get it; that’s what happened to me.&#8221;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com/la-femme-du-fromage-cheese-connoisseur/">A Small and Mighty Venture</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cheeseconnoisseur.com">Cheese Connoisseur</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
